Okay, so Entropic just released Sonnet
4.5, which I think is going to be one of
their most consequential release at the
moment. It's the best coding model
available to date. But more
interestingly, it can do up to 30 hours
of focused agentic coding, which really
breaks the trends that we have been
seeing. It also has some very
interesting features. For example, it's
now context aware. So it can keep track
of how many tokens it has used and it's
not overzealous anymore. So it focuses
on a few task at a time rather than
trying to attempt to do everything all
at once. And it's not just the model.
Entropics is actually releasing a number
of different tools including what
they're calling cloud code SDK. They are
also releasing a number of different
other tools including cloud agent SDK
where you can use cloud code in your own
applications. They're also releasing
imagine with cloud. This is a new way of
building software. Okay. So let's have a
quick look at this release. Now
something you will notice is that the
language that they're using now is very
different from the blog post. So they
say cloud sonet 4.5 is the best coding
model in the world. They're not saying
that it's their best coding model. It's
the strongest model for building complex
agents. It's the best model at using
computers and it shows substantial gain
in reasoning and mathematics. So some of
the updates they have a new version of
cloud code that has added checkpoints.
According to them this was one of the
most requested features. They are also
releasing a native VS code extension
which is going to be really good
especially for people who are using VS
code and now you also have a context
editing feature in memory tool within
the cloud API. So within the cloud API
they are introducing these new
parameters. I'll probably create another
video on this, but this will help you
intelligently manage the context of your
agent when you're using the cloud API.
And as I said in the beginning, they're
also releasing cloud agent SDK. This is
their internal tool which you can use to
build software using the cloud SDK. But
one thing, they're not changing the
pricing. So this is in contrast to all
the other Frontier Labs who are trying
to save on cost or at least release
versions that are lower at cost. They're
keeping the pricing to exactly the same
as they have for the previous version of
Cloud Sonnet. So you're probably getting
more intelligence at the same cost. And
when we talk about intelligence, the
main application that Entropic is
focusing is coding. And now this is the
best state-of-the-art model available on
market for coding related tasks.
Specifically, if you look at sweep bench
verified with parallel test time
compute, it gets to 82%.
Gemini 2.5 Pro is at 67%.
We are expecting a release of Gemini 3
probably mid October. That's hopefully
is going to be able to compete somewhere
here. But hands down, it beats even the
previous version of Opus 4.1. This is
probably the best coding model at the
moment. Now, it's also specifically
trained for computer use. And in fact,
they say that on the OS world benchmark
that's test AI models on real world
computer usage, the previous version of
Sonnet 4 had an accuracy of 42.2%.
Now it's 61.4%
which is almost five 50% jump and that's
why I think they are calling it a major
version bump. This is also now powering
the clot for Chrome that is an extension
you can use to control Chrome browser. I
think I already created a video on this.
It's a pretty neat because you can
assign tasks to cloud and it will be
able to do those on Chrome. So it's a
very first iteration of their agentic
browsing experience that is controlled
by cloud. So now it's going to be
powered by Sonnet 4.5. Now if you look
at some of the other benchmarks, this
model is state-of-the-art hands down. We
looked at bench verified but if you look
at agentic terminal coding this is
terminal bench again it's
state-of-the-art and the improvement is
actually substantial now on agentic tool
use to two benchmark again it's
state-of-the-art in almost all
categories probably except the retail
one whereos
4.1 is still the best model but it's
only by6%.
So not a significance difference at all.
Entropic really has figured out a recipe
of building great coding models and it's
also specifically at domains that are
verifiable in nature. So for example,
finance, law, medicine and STEM. They
show state-of-the-art performance. Now
the main usage is going to be how good
this model is in your own application.
So I'll highly recommend to test it out.
But something I want to highlight and
they say that practically speaking we
have observed that it can maintain focus
for more than 30 hours on complex
multi-step tasks. This kind of breaks
the pattern. So here is a plot from
matter where they're measuring the AI
ability to complete long tasks. The
theory is that every 7 months the
duration of the task that an AI can
complete doubles. But if you look here,
GPD5 was released August 2025. So that's
almost a month ago. And it can do almost
two hours of focus training. But now
within a month, we have Sonnet 4.5 that
can do 30 hours of focus training, which
is kind of incredible, right? So it can
really show you the acceleration that is
happening when it comes specifically to
software engineering. So we were
expected to be able to complete around 4
hours of task somewhere in 2026 but now
this model is already able to do 30
hours of focus training or for focused
coding within a month. So we are on a
crazy trajectory. Okay. So a few other
capabilities when it comes to agentic
coding. So set 4.5 can work
independently for ours. We talked about
this and the most useful thing is going
to be that it can focus on a few tasks
at a time rather than trying to attempt
everything all at once. That has been
one of the biggest issue with cloud
models. they try to do way too much and
end up changing a lot of code base that
is already working and sometimes adds a
lot of code that is not useful at all.
Right? So hopefully with this now it's
going to be doing much more targeted
changes and I think people are going to
start coming back to cloud code if it
lives up to the expectation. Another
thing is that it's context awareness. So
clock can now track its token usage
throughout conversation, receiving
updates after each two call. This
awareness helps prevent premature task
abandonment and enables more effective
execution on longunning tasks. So they
specifically are adding something called
context awareness. Essentially the model
is now able to use its context window a
lot more effectively if it's going
through multi-turn conversation. So not
only it can track the number of tokens
it's going to be using but it will also
be able to remove things from context if
they are not important anymore. Now
context awareness I think is going to be
only available with extended thinking.
So you'll have to enable extended
thinking in order to use these
capabilities. So in the beginning of the
conversation you tell it how many tokens
it has access to. So that's going to be
the context window and then based on
that it's going to keep track of how
many tokens it's using at the moment or
how many are remaining and it's going to
be a lot more token efficient. So
hopefully this will also translate it to
cost reduction as well. So Gemini a
couple of days ago introduced a new
version of 2.5 flash and 2.5 light which
are a lot more context efficient or
token efficient. So it gives you much
better performance at a much lower token
usage and hence token cost. And this is
a trend that has been seen for a while
now that the model providers are trying
to create models that are a lot more
token efficient especially with the
reasoning because with reasoning you are
generating a lot more tokens and hence
even if you reduce the cost you will end
up using more tokens. So you're going to
be paying more for the same number of
API calls. Now it also has enhanced tool
usage. So it can now effectively use
tools when it's doing multiple parallel
tool calls. And also this is their most
aligned model to date. Safety is an
integral part of the constitution of
anthropic and they really take it
seriously. So if you look at the
misaligned behavior, this model at the
moment is the best aligned model which
is especially critical for regulated
areas. As if you were working in
finance, law, medicine, even general
user behavior, you want to have a very
well aligned model in enterprises,
right? So entropics focus has mostly
been on enterprises and business
customers or and coding. So it's very
critical for them to have very well
aligned model and seems like with sonnet
4.5 they are able to achieve it which is
pretty incredible. Now on this their
risk assessment framework which they're
calling AI safety levels. So this is
level three which also means that it
might flag certain content when you are
interacting with sonnet 4.4 4 4.5 but
they have made it easy for user to
continue any interrupted conversation
with the sonnet models. Now they're also
releasing what they're calling cloud
agent SDK. So this is built on top of
cloud code. Here they say that we have
solved hard problems. How agents should
manage memory across longunning tasks.
How to handle permission systems that
balance autonomy with user control and
how to coordinate sub aents working
towards a shared goal. So this is going
to be an SDK that you can use in your
own applications for building multi-
aent systems very similar to the agent
SDK from OpenAI but it can use cloth
code as an orchestrator right so I'll
probably have a closer look at this and
maybe create more content on it if
you're interested make sure you
subscribe to the channel they're also
releasing imagine with cloud instead of
planning a task well ahead of time. Now
cloud is going to generate code or user
interfaces for you and then iteratively
refine it as it looks at its output that
it's generating. This is I think an
early preview. I'll probably want to
have a look at it further before making
some more content on it. [snorts] Now
it's already available in cloud and I
believe it's already available on cloud
code as well. So, I'll probably have
another video in which I actually test
the model out, but I wanted to create
this quick update video on what is
inside 4.5. So, do let me know how your
experience with Sonnet 4.5 is. Do you
actually think it's a major upgrade? And
I think this month is going to be pretty
exciting because later early next week,
we're going to have Dev Day from OpenAI
where some very interesting things are
expected. And later in the month, we're
going to have Gemini 3. This might
actually push some of these updates
earlier. We'll have to see. Anyways, I
hope you found this video useful. Thanks
for watching, and as always, see you in
the next one.